# 兄弟的兄弟哦 那麼歡迎我是不是 嘿
My buddy’s buddy. She’s so excited to see me, right? Heh
# 別咬我啊 聽話 趴下
Don’t bite me! Lie down, be a good girl!
# 趴下 別動
Lie down! Freeze!
# 哈哈哈 太嚇人了
Hahaha, it’s too scary!
# 聽話 趴下
Lie down. Be a good girl!
# 你看 這麼兇 這個是母的哦
Look! She’s so fierce. This is a girl, you know.
# 你看 秋天 這個花都開啦
Look! It’s autumn now and the flowers have already blossomed.
# 這是五倍子花
These are the flowers of nutgalls.
# 好香啊 淡淡的 香味
It smells so good. The fragrance, a subtle one.
# 一樹都是
They’re all over the tree.
# 你看 這個是
Look! This is…
# 我們這邊叫甚麼 金ang子
How do we call it here? “Jin ang zi”
# 它這個表面的刺
They can be used to make infused liquor,
# 把它搞掉然後用來 泡酒也可以
after removing the spikes on its surface.
# 那個 直接吃也可以 但是要把裡面的籽要去掉哦
Actually, it can be eaten right away, in fact. But the seeds inside need to be removed first.
# 今年的果 今年的野果都是很
The fruits this yere, the wild fruits this year are really,
# 很多的哦 今年都是豐收年
really plentiful, you know! This is a year of Bumper Yield.
# 你看 這還有bi子(杮子)哦
Look! Here are also “bi zi” (persimmon),
# 小bi子(杮子)
tiny “bi zi”.
# 不是很大的那種 很是很甜的那種
These are not that big, but are really sweet.
# 你看 這裡有一棵個黃花倒水蓮哦
Look! Here is a milkwort (transliteration: Huanghua daoshuilian).
# 這個可以用來煲雞湯的
This can used to make a chicken soup.
# 它的根可以用來煲雞湯的
Its root can be used to make a chicken soup.
# 特別好吃
It’s really tasty.
# 我去借個鋤頭來
Let me borrow a hoe,
# 把它挖回家
and dig it back home.
# 你看 這上還有小黃梨
Look! Here are also some “little brown pears” (a kind of wild fruits) up there.
# 搞一點來吃 這個應該 要煮熟了才可以吃的這個
Let me pick some. I think, they need to be cooked first, before they can be eaten.
# 很澀的哦
It has a strong astringent taste, you know.
# 好多啊
Really a lot!
# 一串都是
A whole string of them
# 你看 這就是 像不像小梨
Look! Here they are. Do they look like little pears?
# 我們這野生的小黃梨就這樣子的
These are the wild “little brown pears” here at our place.
# 嗯 好澀的這個
Um! It's really astringent!
# 甜甜的澀澀的
It’s a bit sweet and astringent.
# 不是很 不是澀澀 是很澀
It’s not very... not a bit astringent, but pretty astringent.
# 以前還小的時候 用那個水煮一下
We used to blanche them in water when we were small.
# 也可以吃的 當零食吃
They can also be, eaten as snacks.
# 煮了之後它就沒那麼澀啦
They’re less astringent after being blanched.
# 就一個個可以當零食吃就這樣
Then they can be eaten as snacks. Eat the whole thing, see?
# 吃完就可以了
Just eat the whole thing.
# 剛剛吃了那個黃梨啊 好澀啊
I’ve just eaten the “little brown pears”. So astringent!
# 搞個糖吃一下 中和一下
To neutralise it, let me get some honey.
# 這個多糖啦 這個都有一斤那麼多
Here’s a lot of honey. It’s around half a kilogram. So much!
# 我去把個 那個 那個根挖出來
Let me go and then, you know, I mean, dig the root out.
# 今天沒穿長褲 穿個短褲過來
I am not wearing trousers today. I’m now in my pants.
# 但是 不影響哦
But, it doesn’t matter.
# 一樣可以挖回家
I can still dig it back home.
# 看下兄弟家
Let me see if my buddy,
# 看下 看下兄弟家有沒有雞
see, see if my buddy has any chickens here.
# 搞隻雞來
Let me fetch a chicken.
# 才叫完美
It would be perfect!
# 兄弟家的這個黃花倒水蓮
Buddy’s, buddy’s milkworts,
# 再配上兄弟家的雞
and buddy’s chicken,
# 加上我家的鹽
together with my salt,
# 絕對是絕配
is absolutely a perfect combination.
# 你看 夠大吧
Look! It’s big, isn’t it?
# 這個樹枝不要的這個
I don’t need the, the branches here.
# 好啦 要把它洗乾淨來
Alright! Let me wash it.
# 去溝裡面洗一下
Let me wash it in the stream.
# 你看 搞定
Look! It’s done!
# 就用這個根 來煲湯
I’m gonna just use this root, to make a soup.
# 其它的就不要 只要根
I'll throw away the rest, keeping only the root.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 先去洗一下 清理一下 503
Let me wash it, clean it first.
# 哎呀 好舒服啊
Aya! It’s so great.
# 這裡用山泉水洗一下腳吧
Let me wash my feet in the spring water first.
# 舒服
Wonderful!
# 你看 這樣洗一下 洗完就很漂亮啦
Look! It would be really pretty, after being washed.
# 這個要曬乾來的哦
It needs to be dried under the sun first, you know.
# 不是說直接煲的
It can’t be used right away.
# 兄弟一臉不情願 他說挖了好多 沒事
My buddy looks very upset. He said that I’ve taken too much. No worries. I'm gonna,
# 到時他 叫他一起吃 一起來吃就好啦
I’m gonna, ask him to enjoy, enjoy with us. He would be fine.
# 山泉水 最舒服
Spring water, is always the best.
# 好啦 就搞了那麼一點點 一大棵
Alright! So just a tiny little bit here, from such a big plant.
# 可以啦 收工收工
Alright! Let’s go, let’s go.
# 回去 曬乾來
Let’s go home, dry them,
# 搞隻雞來燉
fetch a chicken, and stew everything.
# 這個味道絕對OK
The taste would be absolutely OK.
# 可以啦 就這一捆
Alright! Just a bunch here.
# 總算沒有白來
At least this trip is worthy.
# 等一下我帶回去 看下兄弟在幹嘛
I’ll take it back in a while. Let’s see what my buddy is doing.
# 我也會 我朼會搖啦 我也會割啦
Now I also, I can also rip the honey. I can harvest honey now.
# 全都是蜜
It’s filled with honey.
# 割 割這個糖也要有技術的哦 沒有技術割不了
Har, harvesting honey requires skills, you know. Without the skills, it’s impossible to do it right.
# 好多啊 全往下留[SIC]啦
A lot! It’s all flowing down.
# 你看 這個 晶瑩剔透
Look! It’s, crystal clear.
# 哇 這個過濾網 這個濾網過完之後就那個
Wa! This filtering net, after being filtered with this net, it would be, you know,
# 就很漂亮的蜜啦
the honey would be really pretty.
# 你看這個過濾網 過了之後就很乾淨啦
Have a look at this filtering net. The honey would become very pretty after filtering.
# 來 乾杯
C’mon! Cheers!
# 啊~
Ah!
# 誒呀 好甜啊
Eya! It’s really sweet.
# 有那花粉的味道
There’s a scent of pollen.
# 啊~
Ah!
# 好啦好啦 不要淹在這裡 去採蜜
Alright, alright! Don’t get drown here. Go and collect the nectar.
# 這裡都差不多五十斤 很快呦
It’s already almost twenty five kilograms here. It doesn’t take long.
# 這個雞用那個恭花倒水蓮來燉了
These chickens are to be stewed with the milkwort.
# 這是蘆花雞來喲 這個
These are Luhua chickens, you know.
# 這個 這個是黃花倒水蓮
This is, this is the milkwort.
# 曬的不是很乾 本來要曬乾了味道更好
It’s not really that dry. It would taste much better if it's dried for a longer time, in fact.
# 現在逼不及待的
But now I can’t wait any longer.
# 先 先燉幾隻雞來
Let me, let me stew with a couple of chickens first,
# 試一下效果
and see if it’s good.
# 好 慢慢燉 要燉一個小時左右哇
Alright! It takes time. It needs to be stewed for around an hour,
# 才把那個雞的味道燉出來
so that the flavour of chickens can be released.
# 現在這樣生火 要等一下
That’s how we set the fire now. It needs a while.
# 等下它自然回一下火就好啦
It will glow itself. I don't need to take care of it.
# 從白天燉到晚上
From daylight to the evening
# 味道絕對OK
The taste is absolutely OK.
# 放點監
Put some salt.
# 別掉了哦 掉了就麻煩了
Don’t drop. It would be a disaster otherwise.
# 嘗一下
Let me try.
# 這個雞那個高 你看 它的腳你看 那麼高
This chicken is so tall. Look! Its foot, see? It’s so long.
# 我們家的小母雞都是小短腿 她的怎麼那高的腿
The feet of my little hens here are all tiny and short. Why are its feet so long?
# 大長腿
A big long foot
# 嗯 果然不錯哦
Um! It’s really not bad.
# 蘆花雞就是不于樣
Luhua chickens are really different.
# 肉質很緊
The meat is firm.
# 你們想不想吃
Do you want it?
# 哈
Hm?
# 想不想吃
Do you?
# 想吃要等一下啊 我吃完來
You gotta wait. Let me, finish first.
# 我吃肉 你們吃骨頭
Meat is mine, the bone is yours.
# 要好好帶崽 誒呦 你舔到沒有
Take good care of your children, alright? Eya! Did you lick it?
# 沒有 沒舔到
No, you didn’t.
# 給老母狗吃
It’s for the great mom.
# 老母狗最辛苦 老母狗
The great mom is always having a hard time, this great mom.
# 湯也好吃哦
The soup is also very tasty.
# 這樣搖一搖
Swaying it here,
# 很快就冷了的
can cool it down very quickly.
# 香味
Good scent!
# 啥味都沒有 就除了香味 就是香味
Nothing else, apart form good scent, there's still only good scent,
# 雞味
scent of chicken!
# 要嘗嘗 味道都沒有嘗出來
Let me try again. I haven’t tried enough.
# 搞雞抓吃一下
Let me get a chicken foot,
# 搞個雞翅吃一下
get a chicken wing.
# 你看 這種雞的骨頭好大的
Look! This kind of chickens have very big bones,
# 就是沒甚麼肉
but not too much meat.
# 這種雞適合煲湯特別好吃
They're good for making soups. It's exceptionally tasty.
# 連肥肉都沒有
There’s even hardly any fat.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 吃飯啦
It’s time for dinner now.
# 大家都等著吃這個 這鍋雞湯
Everybody is waiting, waiting for this chicken soup.
# 全都人都看著我吃
Everybody is watching me eating.
# 搞很我再也不好意思啦
It makes me feel very embarrassed.